We are stealing nature from our children.
نحن نسرق الطبيعة من أطفالنا.
Now, when I say this, I don't mean that we are destroying nature
حينما أقول هذا، فأنا لا أقصد أنّنا ندمّر الطبيعة
that they will have wanted us to preserve,
التي سيودون لو أنّنا حافظنا عليها،
although that is unfortunately also the case.
رغم أنّ هذا مع الأسف وارد أيضاً.
What I mean here is that we've started to define nature in a way
ما أقصده هنا هو أنّنا بدأنا في تعريف الطبيعة بطريقة
that's so purist and so strict
نقية وصارمة
that under the definition we're creating for ourselves,
أننا تحت هذا التعريف الذي خلقناه لأنفسنا،
there won't be any nature left for our children
فلن يتبقى شيء من هذه الطبيعة لأطفالنا
when they're adults.
حينما يبلغون سن الرشد.
But there's a fix for this.
لكن هناك حل لهذا.
So let me explain.
لذا دعوني أشرحه.
Right now, humans use half of the world
في الوقت الراهن، يستغل البشر نصف العالم
to live, to grow their crops and their timber,
من أجل العيش والزراعة وجمع الحطب،
to pasture their animals.
ولرعي مواشيهم.
If you added up all the human beings,
إذا حسبتم مجموع كل البشر
we would weigh 10 times as much as all the wild mammals put together.
فسيصل مجموعنا إلى 10 أضعاف مجموع الثدييات البرية جميعها.
We cut roads through the forest.
نشق طرقاً في الغابات.
We have added little plastic particles to the sand on ocean beaches.
أضفنا جزيئات بلاستيكية صغيرة على رمال شواطئ المحيطات.
We've changed the chemistry of the soil with our artificial fertilizers.
غيرنا كيمياء التربة باستخدامنا للأسمدة الصناعية.
And of course, we've changed the chemistry of the air.
وبطبيعة الحال، غيرنا كيمياء الهواء.
So when you take your next breath,
لذا، حينما تتنفس في المرة القادمة،
you'll be breathing in 42 percent more carbon dioxide
فستنتشق 42 في المئة من ثاني أكسيد الكربون
than if you were breathing in 1750.
مما كنت ستستنشقه سنة 1750.
So all of these changes, and many others,
إذاً فكل هذه التغيرات، والعديد غيرها،
have come to be kind of lumped together under this rubric of the "Anthropocene."
قد أصبحت منضوية تحت عنوان: "عصر الأنثروبوسين"
And this is a term that some geologists are suggesting
وهذا مصطلح اقترحه بعض الجيولوجيون
we should give to our current epoch,
لنلقب به عصرنا الحالي،
given how pervasive human influence has been over it.
بالنظر للتأثير المهول للإنسان فيه.
Now, it's still just a proposed epoch, but I think it's a helpful way
الآن، ما تزال هذه مجرد مرحلة مقترحة، لكنني أعتقد أنها طريقة مفيدة
to think about the magnitude of human influence on the planet.
للتفكير في مدى تأثير الإنسان على الكوكب.
So where does this put nature?
إذاً، أين يضع هذا الطبيعة؟
What counts as nature in a world where everything is influenced by humans?
ما الذي يمكن اعتباره طبيعة في عالم يؤثر فيه الإنسان على كل شيء؟
So 25 years ago, environmental writer Bill McKibben said
منذ 25 سنة خلت، قال الكاتب البيئي (بيل مكيبان):
that because nature was a thing apart from man
أنه بسبب بعد الطبيعة عن الإنسان
and because climate change meant
ولأن تغير المناخ كان يعني
that every centimeter of the Earth was altered by man,
أن الإنسان غيّر كل سنتيمتر من الأرض،
then nature was over.
فإن الطبيعة قد انتهت.
In fact, he called his book "The End of Nature."
في الواقع فقد أسمى كتابه "نهاية الطبيعة."
I disagree with this. I just disagree with this.
أنا أختلف مع هذا. أختلف معه تماماًَ.
I disagree with this definition of nature, because, fundamentally, we are animals.
أختلف مع تعريف الطبيعة هذا، لأننا بالأساس حيوانات.
Right? Like, we evolved on this planet
أليس كذلك؟ أعني، لقد تطوّرنا على هذا الكوكب
in the context of all the other animals with which we share a planet,
في نطاق جميع الحيوانات الأخرى التي نتقاسم معها هذا الكوكب،
and all the other plants, and all the other microbes.
وكل النباتات الأخرى، وكل الميكروبات الأخرى.
And so I think that nature
وبهذا أعتقد أن الطبيعة
is not that which is untouched by humanity, man or woman.
ليس تلك التي لم تلمسها الإنسانية، رجلاً كان أو امرأة.
I think that nature is anywhere where life thrives,
أعتقد أن الطبيعة هي أي مكان تزدهر فيه الحياة،
anywhere where there are multiple species together,
أي مكان توجد به أنواع متعددة مع بعضها البعض،
anywhere that's green and blue and thriving and filled with life
أي مكان أخضر أو أزرق مزدهر ومفعم بالحياة
and growing.
ونام.
And under that definition,
وتحت هذا التعريف،
things look a little bit different.
تبدو الأشياء مختلفة شيئا ما.
Now, I understand that there are certain parts of this nature
الآن، أفهم أن هناك أجزاء معينة من هذه الطبيعة
that speak to us in a special way.
تخاطبنا بطريقة خاصة جداً.
Places like Yellowstone,
أمكنة مثل محمية ييلوستون في أمريكا،
or the Mongolian steppe,
أو السهوب المنغولية،
or the Great Barrier Reef
أو الحاجز المرجاني العظيم في إستراليا
or the Serengeti.
أو محمية سيرنجيتي في تنزانيا.
Places that we think of as kind of Edenic representations
أمكنة نعتقد أنها تمثيلات الجنة
of a nature before we screwed everything up.
للطبيعة قبل أن ندمر كل شيء.
And in a way, they are less impacted by our day to day activities.
وبشكل ما، فهي متأثرة بشكل أقل بنشاط حياتنا اليومية.
Many of these places have no roads or few roads,
العديد من هذه الأمكنة ليست بها طرق، أو طرق قليلة،
so on, like such.
أو شيء من هذا القبيل.
But ultimately, even these Edens are deeply influenced by humans.
لكن في النهاية، حتى هذه الجنان، معرضة لتأثير الإنسان بشدة.
Now, let's just take North America, for example,
لنأخذ الآن أمريكا الشمالية مثلاً،
since that's where we're meeting.
بما أنها هي مكان التقائنا.
So between about 15,000 years ago when people first came here,
فبين حوالي 15000 سنة حين جاء البشر هنا لأول مرة،
they started a process of interacting with the nature
بدأوا في عملية التفاعل مع الطبيعة
that led to the extinction of a big slew of large-bodied animals,
الشيء الذي أدى إلى انقراض عدد كبير من الحيوانات الضخمة،
from the mastodon to the giant ground sloth,
من المستودون إلى كسلان الأرض العملاق،
saber-toothed cats,
السنور ذي الأسنان السيفية،
all of these cool animals that unfortunately are no longer with us.
وكل هذه الحيوانات الرائعة التي للأسف لم تعد بيننا.
And when those animals went extinct,
وحين انقرضت هذه الحيوانات،
you know, the ecosystems didn't stand still.
كما تعلمون، لم تهدأ الأنظمة البيئية.
Massive ripple effects changed grasslands into forests,
فقد غيرت التداعيات الكبيرة المراعي إلى غابات،
changed the composition of forest from one tree to another.
وغيرت تركيب الغابة من شجرة إلى أخرى.
So even in these Edens,
إذن فحتى هذه الجنان،
even in these perfect-looking places
حتى في هذه الأماكن الفاتنة
that seem to remind us of a past before humans,
والتي يبدو أنها تذكرنا بالماضي ما قبل الإنسان،
we're essentially looking at a humanized landscape.
فإننا بالأساس ننظر إلى منظر غيره الإنسان.
Not just these prehistoric humans, but historical humans, indigenous people
ليس فقط إنسان ما قبل التاريخ، لكن إنسان التاريخي، السكان الأصليين
all the way up until the moment when the first colonizers showed up.
حتى اللحظة التي ظهر فيها أول المحتلون.
And the case is the same for the other continents as well.
والحال كذلك بالنسبة للقارات الأخرى أيضاً.
Humans have just been involved in nature
كان البشر على علاقة بالطبيعة
in a very influential way for a very long time.
بطريقة مؤثرة جداً ولوقت طويل.
Now, just recently, someone told me,
مؤخراً فقط، أخبرني شخص ما،
"Oh, but there are still wild places."
"أوه، لكن ماتزال هناك مناطق برية."
And I said, "Where? Where? I want to go."
فقلت: "أين؟ أين؟ أريد أن أذهب إلى هناك."
And he said, "The Amazon."
فقال، "الأمازون."
And I was like, "Oh, the Amazon. I was just there.
كان لسان حالي أشبه ب، "آه، الأمازون. كنت هناك للتو.
It's awesome. National Geographic sent me to Manú National Park,
إنه مكان رائع. أرسلتني ناشيونال جيوغرافيك إلى حديقة مانو الوطنية،
which is in the Peruvian Amazon,
وهي في الأمازون البيروفية،
but it's a big chunk of rainforest, uncleared, no roads,
لكنها عبارة عن غابات مطرية كثيفة غير معبدة، ليست بها طرق،
protected as a national park,
وهي محمية كحديقة وطنية،
one of the most, in fact, biodiverse parks in the world.
وهي في الواقع، واحدة من أكثر الحدائق تنوعاً في العالم.
And when I got in there with my canoe, what did I find, but people.
وحينما وصلت إلى هناك بزورقي، لم أجد غير الناس!
People have been living there for hundreds and thousands of years.
يعيش الناس هناك منذ مئات وآلاف السنين.
People live there, and they don't just float over the jungle.
يعيش الناس هناك، ولا يطفون فقط عبر الأدغال.
They have a meaningful relationship with the landscape.
لديهم علاقة ذات مغزى مع المناظر الطبيعية.
They hunt. They grow crops.
يقنصون، ويزرعون المحاصيل.
They domesticate crops.
ويخزنون المحاصيل.
They use the natural resources to build their houses,
يستعملون المصادر الطبيعية لبناء منازلهم،
to thatch their houses.
ولتسقيف منازلهم.
They even make pets out of animals that we consider to be wild animals.
حتى أنهم يتخذون حيوانات أليفة من حيوانات نعتبرها برية.
These people are there
هؤلاء الناس موجودون هناك
and they're interacting with the environment
ويتفاعلون مع البيئة
in a way that's really meaningful and that you can see in the environment.
بطريقة ذات مغزى كبير والتي يمكنكم رؤيتها في البيئة.
Now, I was with an anthropologist on this trip,
كنت بصحبة عالم آنثروبولوجيا في هذه الرحلة،
and he told me, as we were floating down the river,
وقد قال لي، ونحن نطفو خلال النهر،
he said, "There are no demographic voids in the Amazon."
قال، "ليست هناك فراغات ديموغرافية في الأمازون"
This statement has really stuck with me,
وقد علقت هذه العبارة في ذهني حقاً،
because what it means is that the whole Amazon is like this.
لأن ما كانت تعنيه هو أن الأمازون كله هكذا.
There's people everywhere.
الناس موجودون في كل مكان.
And many other tropical forests are the same,
والعديد من الغابات الإستوائية الإخرى تشبه بعضها،
and not just tropical forests.
وليست الغابات الإستوائية فقط.
People have influenced ecosystems in the past,
لقد أثر الناس على الأنظمة البيئية في الماضي،
and they continue to influence them in the present,
ومايزالون مستمرين في ذلك في الوقت الحاضر،
even in places where they're harder to notice.
حتى في أماكن حيث من الصعب ملاحظة ذلك.
So, if all of the definitions of nature that we might want to use
إذاً، إن كانت كل تعاريف الطبيعة التي نود استعمالها،
that involve it being untouched by humanity
والتي تتضمن كونها لم يلمسها إنسان
or not having people in it,
أو لم يتواجد بها شخص،
if all of those actually give us a result where we don't have any nature,
إن كانت كل هذه الأمور تعطينا نتيجة أننا لا نملك طبيعة،
then maybe they're the wrong definitions.
حينها ربما تكون هي التعاريف الخاطئة.
Maybe we should define it by the presence of multiple species,
ربما يجب علينا تعريفها بوجود أنواع متعددة،
by the presence of a thriving life.
بوجود حياة مزدهرة.
Now, if we do it that way,
الآن، إن قمنا بها بتلك الطريقة،
what do we get?
ما الذي سنحصل عليه؟
Well, it's this kind of miracle.
حسناً، إنها هذه المعجزة.
All of a sudden, there's nature all around us.
فجأةً، سنجد طبيعة من حولنا.
we see this Monarch caterpillar
فجأةً، سنرى هذه اليرقة الملكية،
munching on this plant,
وهي تقرض هذه النبتة،
and we realize that there it is,
وسندرك أنها هناك،
and it's in this empty lot in Chattanooga.
وهي في هذه البقعة الفارغة من تشاتانوغا.
And look at this empty lot.
انظروا، إنها بقعة فارغة.
I mean, there's, like, probably,
أقصد ربما، هناك، ربما،
a dozen, minimum, plant species growing there,
على الأقل، عشرات، من النباتات تنمو هناك،
supporting all kinds of insect life,
تدعم كل أنواع الحشرات الحية،
and this is a completely unmanaged space, a completely wild space.
وهي فضاء مهمل، فضاء بري بالكامل.
This is a kind of wild nature right under our nose,
هذه هي الطبيعة البرية هنا أمام أعيننا،
that we don't even notice.
والتي لا نلقي لها بالاً حتى.
And there's an interesting little paradox, too.
وهناك مفارقة صغيرة مثيرة للاهتمام، أيضاً.
So this nature,
إذاً هذه الطبيعة،
this kind of wild, untended part
هذا النوع البري، غير المتدخل فيه
of our urban, peri-urban, suburban agricultural existence
من طرف وجودنا شبه الحضري، و الزراعي وفي الضواحي
that flies under the radar,
الذي يحوم حولنا،
it's arguably more wild than a national park,
هي ربما أكثر برية من حديقة وطنية،
because national parks are very carefully managed
لأن الحديقة الوطنية مسيرة بشكل دقيق جداً
in the 21st century.
في القرن 21.
Crater Lake in southern Oregon, which is my closest national park,
(بحيرة كارتر) في أوريغون الجنوبية، وهي أقرب حديقة وطنية لي،
is a beautiful example of a landscape that seems to be coming out of the past.
هي مثال جميل لمنظر طبيعي يبدو وكأنه قادم من رحم الماضي.
But they're managing it carefully.
لكنهم يسيرونها بشكل دقيق.
One of the issues they have now is white bark pine die-off.
أحد المشاكل التي يواجهونها الآن هي موت الصنوبر أبيض الساق.
White bark pine is a beautiful, charismatic --
الصنوبر أبيض الساق جميل وجذاب--
I'll say it's a charismatic megaflora
وسأقول أنها نبتة ضخمة جذابة.
that grows up at high altitude --
والتي تنمو في المرتفعات--
and it's got all these problems right now with disease.
وهي تعاني من كل هذه المشاكل الآن بسبب المرض.
There's a blister rust that was introduced,
كما ظهر الصدأ المنفّط (مرض فطري يصيب النبات)،
bark beetle.
خنفساء اللحاء.
So to deal with this, the park service has been planting
وللتعامل مع هذا المشكل، قامت إدارة الحديقة بغرس
rust-resistant white bark pine seedlings in the park,
شتلات صنوبر أبيض الساق مقاومة للصدأ في الحديقة،
even in areas that they are otherwise managing as wilderness.
حتى في مناطق يديرونها على أنها برية.
And they're also putting out beetle repellent in key areas
وهم يضعون أيضاً طارد الخنفساء في مناطق مهمة
as I saw last time I went hiking there.
كما رأيت مؤخراً حين ذهبت هناك للتمشي.
And this kind of thing is really much more common than you would think.
وهذه الأمور متعارف عليها أكثر بكثير مما تظنون.
National parks are heavily managed.
تحظى الحدائق الوطنية باهتمام كبير.
The wildlife is kept to a certain population size and structure.
يتم الحفاظ على الحياة البرية إلى حدود نسبة سكان وبنية معينتين.
Fires are suppressed.
يتم إخماد النيران.
Fires are started.
ويتم إضرام النيران.
Non-native species are removed.
يتم إزالة الأنواع غير الأصلية.
Native species are reintroduced.
ويتم إعادة الأنواع الأصلية.
And in fact, I took a look,
في الواقع، ألقيت نظرة،
and Banff National Park is doing all of the things I just listed:
ورأيت أن الحديقة الوطنية ببانف تقوم بكل ما عددته:
suppressing fire, having fire,
إخماد وإضرام النيران،
radio-collaring wolves, reintroducing bison.
تطويق الذئاب بأطواق تعقب، وإعادة حيوان البيسون.
It takes a lot of work to make these places look untouched.
يتطلب جعل هذه الأماكن تبدو بِكْرَاً، جهداً كبيراً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And in a further irony, these places that we love the most
ومن السخرية، أن هذه الأماكن التي نحبها أكثر
are the places that we love a little too hard, sometimes.
هي الأماكن التي نحبها حبّاً مبالغاً فيه، أحياناً.
A lot of us like to go there,
يحب الكثير منا الذهاب إلى هناك،
and because we're managing them to be stable
ولأننا تحكمنا في جعلها مستقرة
in the face of a changing planet,
على سطح كوكب متغير،
they often are becoming more fragile over time.
فإنها تصبح أكثر حساسية مع مرور الوقت.
Which means that they're the absolute worst places
مما يعني أنها أسوأ الأماكن على الإطلاق
to take your children on vacation,
لتأخذ أولادك إليها في العطلة،
because you can't do anything there.
لأنه لن يمكنك القيام بشيء هناك.
You can't climb the trees.
لن تستطيع تسلق الأشجار.
You can't fish the fish.
لن تستطيع صيد السمك.
You can't make a campfire out in the middle of nowhere.
لن تستطيع إشعال النار وسط المكان.
You can't take home the pinecones.
لن تأخذ المخروط الصنوبري إلى البيت.
There are so many rules and restrictions
هناك العديد من القواعد والقوانين
that from a child's point of view,
من وجهة نظر طفل،
this is, like, the worst nature ever.
ليعتبر هذه الطبيعة الأسوأ على الإطلاق.
Because children don't want to hike
لأن الأطفال لا يريدون التمشي
through a beautiful landscape for five hours
محاطين بمنظر جميل لمدة 5 ساعات
and then look at a beautiful view.
ليتأملوا بعدها منظراً جميلاً.
That's maybe what we want to do as adults,
هذا ربما ما نريد القيام به كبالغين،
but what kids want to do is hunker down in one spot
لكن ما يرغب طفل في فعله هو أن يجلس في مكان واحد
and just tinker with it, just work with it,
ليعبث ويعمل فيه فحسب،
just pick it up, build a house, build a fort, do something like that.
يأخذه، ويبني منزلاً، يبني قلعة، أشياء كهذه.
Additionally, these sort of Edenic places
بالإضافة إلى ذلك، هذه الأنواع من الجنان
are often distant from where people live.
غالباً ما تكون بعيدة عن مكان عيش الناس.
And they're expensive to get to. They're hard to visit.
ويكون الوصول إليها مكلفاً. ويصعب زيارتها.
So this means that they're only available to the elites,
مما يعني أنها متاحة فقط للنخبة،
and that's a real problem.
وهذه مشكلة حقيقية.
The Nature Conservancy did a survey of young people,
أجرت منظمة حفظ الطبيعة دراسة استهدفت الشباب،
and they asked them, how often do you spend time outdoors?
وسألوهم، كم من الوقت تقضونه في الخارج؟
And only two out of five spent time outdoors
فكان 2 من كل 5 فقط يقضون وقتاً في الخارج
at least once a week.
مرة في الأسبوع على الأقل.
The other three out of five were just staying inside.
والثلاثة من 5 الآخرين كانوا يقضون وقتهم في البيت.
And when they asked them why, what are the barriers to going outside,
وحين سألوهم لماذا، ماهي العراقيل التي تمنعهم من الخروج،
the response of 61 percent was,
كان جواب 61 % منهم،
"There are no natural areas near my home."
"ليست هناك مناطق طبيعية قرب منزلي."
And this is crazy. This is just patently false.
وهذا جنوني. وهو أمر خاطئ جداً.
I mean, 71 percent of people in the US
أقصد أن 71% من الأمريكيين
live within a 10-minute walk of a city park.
يعيشون على بعد 10 دقائق مشياً من حديقة في المدينة.
And I'm sure the figures are similar in other countries.
وأنا متأكدة من أنّ الأرقام مماثلة في دول أخرى.
And that doesn't even count your back garden,
وهذا لا يشمل حتى حديقتك الخلفية،
the urban creek, the empty lot.
الخليج الحضري، والقطعة الأرضية الفارغة.
Everybody lives near nature.
كل الناس تعيش قرب الطبيعة.
Every kid lives near nature.
كل طفل يعيش قرب الطبيعة.
We've just somehow forgotten how to see it.
لقد نسينا بطريقة ما، كيف نرى ذلك.
We've spent too much time watching David Attenborough documentaries
قضينا وقتاً طويلاً في مشاهدة وثائقيات (دايفيد أتنبوروغ)
where the nature is really sexy --
حيث الطبيعة مثيرة فعلاً--
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
and we've forgotten how to see the nature that is literally right outside our door,
ونسينا كيف نرى الطبيعة التي توجد فعلياً خارج أبواب بيوتنا،
the nature of the street tree.
طبيعة الأشجار الموجودة في الشارع.
So here's an example: Philadelphia.
إليكم هذا المثال: فيلاديفيا.
There's this cool elevated railway
هناك سكة حديدية معلقة رائعة
that you can see from the ground, that's been abandoned.
يمكنك رؤيتها من الأرض، والتي تم التخلي عنها.
Now, this may sound like the beginning of the High Line story in Manhattan,
الآن، قد يبدو هذا وكأنها بداية لقصة (هاي لاين) في مانهاتن،
and it's very similar, except they haven't developed this into a park yet,
وهي قريبة جداً، إلا أنهم لم يطوروها بعد إلى حديقة،
although they're working on it.
مع أنهم بصدد العمل عليها.
So for now, it's still this little sort of secret wilderness
لذا فالآن، ما يزال هناك ذلك النوع من البرية السرية
in the heart of Philadelphia,
في قلب فيلاديلفيا،
and if you know where the hole is in the chain-link fence,
وإن كنتم تعرفون أين يوجد الثقب في سلسلة السياج،
you can scramble up to the top
يمكنكم التسلق نحو الأعلى
and you can find this completely wild meadow
وستجدون ذلك السهل البري تماماً
just floating above the city of Philadelphia.
وهو يطفو فوق مدينة فيلاديلفيا.
Every single one of these plants grew from a seed
نمت كل نبتة من تلك النباتات من بذرة
that planted itself there.
غرست نفسها هناك.
This is completely autonomous, self-willed nature.
هذه طبيعة مستقلة وبرية من تلقاء نفسها.
And it's right in the middle of the city.
وهي متواجدة في قلب المدينة.
And they've sent people up there to do sort of biosurveys,
وهم يرسلون الناس هناك ليقوموا بأبحاث عن الحياة البرية،
and there are over 50 plant species up there.
يوجد أكثر من 50 نوع من النباتات هناك في الأعلى.
And it's not just plants.
وهي ليست نباتات فقط.
This is an ecosystem, a functioning ecosystem.
هذا نظام بيئي، نظام بيئي فعال.
It's creating soil. It's sequestering carbon.
فهي تخلق التراب، تعزل الكاربون.
There's pollination going on.
كما أن هنالك عملية تلقيح تحدث.
I mean, this is really an ecosystem.
أقصد أنه نظام بيئي حقيقي.
So scientists have started calling ecosystems like these "novel ecosystems,"
لذا فقد بدأ العلماء في تسمية أنظمة كهذه ب"الأنظمة البيئية الجديدة،"
because they're often dominated by non-native species,
لأنه غالباً ما تسيطر عليها كائنات غير أصلية،
and because they're just super weird.
ولأنها غريبة جداً.
They're just unlike anything we've ever seen before.
فهي مختلفة عن أي شيء رأيناه من قبل.
For so long, we dismissed all these novel ecosystems as trash.
لوقت طويل، تجاهلنا كل هذه الأنظمة البيئية الجديدة باعتبارها أماكن للقمامة.
We're talking about regrown agricultural fields,
نتحدث عن الأراضي الزراعية التي أعيدت تنميتها،
timber plantations that are not being managed on a day-to-day basis,
الأغراس التي لا يتم تسييرها بشكل يومي،
second-growth forests generally, the entire East Coast,
غابات تنمو للمرة الثانية عموما، في الساحل الشرقي بأكمله،
where after agriculture moved west, the forest sprung up.
بعدما تم نقل الزراعة غرباً، اتتشرت الغابة.
And of course, pretty much all of Hawaii,
وبالطبع، معظم هاواي،
where novel ecosystems are the norm,
حيث الأنظمة البيئية الجديدة هي العادة،
where exotic species totally dominate.
حيث تسيطر الكائنات الغريبة سيطرة تامة.
This forest here has Queensland maple,
هذه الغابة تمتلك قيقب كويزلاند،
it has sword ferns from Southeast Asia.
وبها سرخسيات سيفية من جنوب شرق آسيا.
You can make your own novel ecosystem, too.
يمكنك خلق نظامك البيئي الجديد أيضاً.
It's really simple.
وهو أمر سهل جداً.
You just stop mowing your lawn.
عليك فقط أن تتوقف عن قص حديقتك.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Ilkka Hanski was an ecologist in Finland, and he did this experiment himself.
(إيكا هانسكي) عالم بيئي في فنلندا، وقد قام بهذه التجربة بنفسه.
He just stopped mowing his lawn,
توقف عن قص حديقته،
and after a few years, he had some grad students come,
وبعد بضع سنوات، أحضر بعضاً من الطلبة
and they did sort of a bio-blitz of his backyard,
وقاموا بنوع من المداهمة البيئية في حديقته الخلفية،
and they found 375 plant species,
فوجدوا 375 نوع من النباتات،
including two endangered species.
بما فيها اثنتان معرضتان للانقراض.
So when you're up there on that future High Line of Philadelphia,
لذا فحين تكون هناك في (هاي لاين) المقبلة في فيلاديلفيا،
surrounded by this wildness,
محاطاً بهذه الحياة البرية،
surrounded by this diversity, this abundance, this vibrance,
محاطاً بكل هذا التنوع، والوفرة والحيوية،
you can look over the side
يمكنك أن تنظر إلى جانبك
and you can see a local playground for a local school,
وسترى ساحة للعب في مدرسة محلية،
and that's what it looks like.
وهذا ما تبدو عليه.
These children have, that --
هؤلاء الأطفال لديهم، ذلك--
You know, under my definition,
أتعلمون، في تعريفي الخاص،
there's a lot of the planet that counts as nature,
هناك الكثير في هذا الكوكب مما يمكن عدّه طبيعة،
but this would be one of the few places that wouldn't count as nature.
لكن هذا سيكون أحد الأمكنة القليلة التي لا تعدّ من الطبيعة.
And what I really wanted to do
وما أردت القيام به فعلاً
was just, like, throw a ladder over the side
هو أن أرمي سلماً إلى ذلك الجانب
and get all these kids to come up with me into this cool meadow.
وأجعل كل أولئك الأطفال يصعدون و ينضمون إلي في هذا السهل البديع.
In a way, I feel like this is the choice that faces us.
بطريقة ما، أشعر أن هذا هو الخيار المتبقي لنا.
If we dismiss these new natures as not acceptable or trashy or no good,
إذا أهملنا الطبيعة الجديدة على أنها غير مقبولة، أومليئة بالقمامة أو غير جيدة،
we might as well just pave them over.
ربما سنمهد طرقاً فوقها فحسب.
And in a world where everything is changing,
وفي عالم حيث يتغير كل شيء،
we need to be very careful about how we define nature.
علينا أن نكون حذرين جداً في تعريفنا للطبيعة.
In order not to steal it from our children,
لكي لا نسرقها من أطفالنا،
we have to do two things.
علينا أن نقوم بأمرين.
First, we cannot define nature as that which is untouched.
أولاً، لا نستطيع تعريف الطبيعة على أنها تلك التي لم يلمسها إنسان.
This never made any sense anyway.
لم يكن هذا منطقيا قط، على أي حال.
Nature has not been untouched for thousands of years.
لم تكن الطبيعة غير ملموسة لآلاف من السنين.
And it excludes most of the nature that most people can visit
وهذا يستثني أغلب الطبيعة التي يمكن لمعظم الناس زيارتها
and have a relationship with,
وخلق علاقة معها،
including only nature that children cannot touch.
بما في ذلك الغابة التي لا يمكن للأطفال لمسها.
Which brings me to the second thing that we have to do,
وهذا ما يحيلني إلى الشيء الثاني الذي علينا القيام بها،
which is that we have to let children touch nature,
وهو أنه يتوجب علينا أن نترك أطفالنا يلمسون الطبيعة،
because that which is untouched is unloved.
لأن الشيء غير الملموس ليس محبوباً.
(Applause)
(تصفبق)
We face some pretty grim environmental challenges on this planet.
نحن نواجه تحديات بيئية قاتمة على هذا الكوكب.
Climate change is among them.
والتغير المناخي هو أحدها.
There's others too: habitat loss is my favorite thing
وهناك أخرى أيضاً: فقدان المساكن هي أكثر شيء
to freak out about in the middle of the night.
يصيبني بالفزع عند منتصف الليل.
But in order to solve them,
ولكن من أجل حلها،
we need people -- smart, dedicated people --
نحتاج إلى أناس أذكياء ومتفانين --
who care about nature.
ممن يهتمون بالطبيعة.
And the only way we're going to raise up a generation of people
والطريقة الوحيدة التي يمكننا بها تربية جيل من الناس
who care about nature
يهتمون بالطبيعة
is by letting them touch nature.
هو أن نتركهم يلمسون الطبيعة.
I have a Fort Theory of Ecology,
لدي حصن نظري عن علم البيئة،
Fort Theory of Conservation.
حصن نظري عن المحافظة.
Every ecologist I know, every conservation biologist I know,
كل عالم أحياء أعرفه، كل عالم أحياء محافظ أعرفه،
every conservation professional I know,
كل أستاذ محافظة أعرفه،
built forts when they were kids.
بنوا قلاعاً حين كانوا صغاراً.
If we have a generation that doesn't know how to build a fort,
إن كان لدينا جيل لا يعرف كيف يبني قلعة،
we'll have a generation that doesn't know how to care about nature.
سيكون لدينا جيل لا يعرف كيف يهتم بالطبيعة.
I think I would much rather learn from this boy
أعتقد أنه من الأفضل لي أن أتعلم من هذا الطفل
that no matter where this plant comes from,
أنه مهما كان أصل هذه النبتة،
it is beautiful, and it deserves to be touched and appreciated.
فإنها جميلة، وتستحق أن تلمس وأن تقدَّر.
Thank you.
شكرا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)